A Guide to the Lewis F. Powell Jr. Collection 1937-1999
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, Washington and Lee University
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, School of Law, Washington and Lee University
Lewis F. Powell Jr. Collection 1937-1999
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, School of Law, Washington and Lee University
002
c. 21 cubic feet
These materials relating to Lewis F. Powell's life come from a variety of miscellaneous sources and are collected by the Powell Archives. This collection should not be confused with the Lewis F. Powell Jr. Papers, Ms 001. The Powell Papers contain the documentation of Powell's life which he created and maintained.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Scope and Content Information
This open-ended collection comprises discrete gifts of usually small amounts of documentation relating to the life of Justice Powell. These materials come from a variety of sources including friends, associates, and the geneal public. The Powell Archives staff have also added news clippings. Materials separated from the Powell Papers that would, in most cases, have been discarded, are also housed here for possible exhibition or other use not directly related to research. These materials include duplicate speeches,clippings, and Supreme Court slip opinions.
Contents List
- Articles re Powell 1971-2000 (Box 1)
- Bibliographies (Box 1)
- Biographical Summaries (Box 1)
- Interviews 1990-1991 (Box 1)
- Letter: Powell to Chief Justice Preston V. Campbell June 13, 1936 (Box 1)
- Letter: Powell to Dr. Charles D. Haskell January 16, 1937 (Box 1)
- James D. Farrar Correspondence, 1972-1989 (Box 1)
- Fitzgerald Bemiss Correspondence 1955-1994 (Box 1)
- George Blow letters (2) 1972 & 1989 (Box 1)
- Lewis F. Powell Jr. letters to Virginius Dabney (111 leaves), 1971-1994 (Box 1)
  These letters were removed by the donor from the Virginius Dabney Papers, before those papers were given to the University of Virginia Special Collections.
- Louis F. Oberdorfer Corresponcence, October 1989 (Box 1)
  This single exchange begins with Judge Oberdorfer's letter of October 20, 1989 (copy) enclosing a copy of Henry W. Anderson's 1931 report of the Wickersham Commission concerning prohibition of alcohol. Justice Powell's letter of acknowledgement (original) of October 24, 1989 is also here.
- ABA Business Law Section Remarks April 12, 1991 (Box 1)
- Baltimore Orioles Baseball Game May 20, 1993 (Box 1)
- Lewis F. Powell Oral History Interview July 27, 1993 (Box 1)
- Sally Smith Oral History Interview November 7, 1996 (Box 1)
- Powell Death and Funeral 1998
  - Lewis F. Powell III Eulogies for His Mother and Father 1996, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Funeral Program August 31, 1998 (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1998 (Box 1 & oversize folder # 2 in map case)
  - Memorial Service at U.S. Supreme Court May 18, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Symposium in Honor Of Lewis F. Powell's Birth Centenary. National Press Club. Video (dvd) Recording by C-Span2 April 6, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Memorial Service at U.S. Supreme Court May 18, 1999 (Box 1)
  - Audio and Video Tape Recordings 1998 (Box 2)
- Angus Powell Diploma and Cerificate 1936, 1944 (Box 1)
- FBI File 1964-1988
  This is a copy of Lewis F. Powell Jr.'s file provided to the Powell Archives by the Federal Bureau of Investigation through a Freedom of Information Act request.
  - General Correspondence 1964-1983 (Box 3)
  - Supreme Court Background Check (Box 3-4)
  - Threat Investigations 1974-1988 (Box 4)
- Powell Wing Dedication and Symposium April 2-4, 1992
  - Printed Materials and Memorabilia (Box 5 & oversize folder #1 in map case)
  - Video Recordings (Box 6)
- Video Recordings of Constitutional Law Classes at Washington and Lee School of Law March - April, 1989 (Box 7)
  Justice Powell taught seven Constitutional Law classes at Washington and Lee University School of Law between March 15 and April 27, 1989. These recordings are on 3/4" videotape.
- Duplicate and Separated Materials from the Lewis F. Powell Jr. Papers
  - Speeches and Writings 1956-1987 (Box 8-11A)
  - Published Materials 1968-1993 (Box 12-12A)
    Duplicate copies of Ultra and the Army Air Forces in World War II, and of journals or reprints containing writing by or about Powell.
  - Published Court Opinions
    - Supreme Court Slip Opinions 1970-1989 (Box 13-30)
    - United States Court of Appeals for the 4th Circuit 1987-1992 (Box 31)
  - Bakke Decision Scrapbook 1977-1978 (Box 32)
    Four copies of the scrapbook of documents and clippings re the 1978 Supreme Court "reverse discrimination" case.
  - Materials Retained for Exhibit Potential
    - Artifacts and Duplicate Documents (Box 33)
    - Photos and Captions from Supreme Court "Justices In World War II" Exhibit (Box 43-35)
  - Scrapbooks re Retirement from U. S. Supreme Court, 1987-1988 (Box 36)
    Duplicate materials removed from 001 Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Papers at 10.9.3
  - U.S. Court of Appeals Fourth Circuit Printed Opinions, 1987-1992 (Box 36)
    Duplicate materials removed from 001 Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Papers at 11.6.1.2. All of these opinions were written by Powell. Though all are printed, some are unpublished.